the
the snow at home self isolating due
to a post positive covert test but
those two things have in common is
that you cannot be here to give
his lecture so instead i will do
the lecture today
so last time but we were trying
to do is we were trying to
actually complete the proof that when i
have used this or but i've annotated
a control flow graph with assertions that
are locally consistent that if i have
done this and i know that the
assertion at the beginning of potholes
then at the end of the path
this assertion that is annotated there will
hold
and let's quickly recap what we defined
here we defined an execution trace and
this trace recalled pi and one of
these execution traces corresponds to a path
in the control flow graph and it
basically starts at some
initiative program point use your own and
at program point use your you have
this state's sigma zero
so here and then it leads to
some program point you m and at
this program point you you have this
final state sigma m
and then one can simply represent the
strace as a sequence of first of
all these tuples of program points
with memos here these tuples of program
points and states and then you have
these labels so these correspond to the
things that happen in the control photograph
and you simply have a sequence of
these
now okay this is this
and then here was the theory that
we were trying to prove so we
had some sort of mini java program
p and we had some path pie
that was an execution trace that starts
in some program point you and leads
to this program point v and we
had assumed that all program points in
p are annotated with assertions which
locally consistent and then we had said
the program point you is annotated with
a and the program point v is
annotated with b
and if these things hold then we
want to conclude that if the initial
state of pipe
satisfies a then the final state will
satisfy be
and then what we have done is
we have started okay this and annotations
and then we have decided that we
want to do this proof by induction
namely on the length m of this
execution trace
and we had also done the first
step and the first step is if
the path has length zero and then
sort of trivially the end point of
the execution is equal to the start
point and then this sigma zero is
equal to sigma m and the assertions
that we have annotated are both the
same so as the
same b and then the cream sort
of trivially holds
and then we were gearing up to
get into more complicated
into the more complicated steps to base
the induction step and what we needed
there was this proposition here that if
i have some arithmetic expressions t and
e
then it is the same whether i
first update the state
to set x to the value that
this expression he would evaluate to in
the state sigma and then evaluate this
expression t on this entire thing or
alternatively it is also the same if
i simply go in and take my
expression and wherever i find an x
in my in my original expression tea
i simply pop in this eve
and i think this was the point
where you stopped last week so to
convince you of this we will actually
give you a small example where this
does hold and then the actual proof
you will see in the homeworks this
next week so let's consider this example
expression where t is x plus y
and he is to tie
time z
and we have also have a state
another state sigma in this case is
that extra five why is minus one
and z is twenty one
nope this direction
okay and then let's first maybe tackle
the left hand side of this of
this equality that the claim here
and what we do here is will
we
update our state here
and first of all we check what
he evaluates to interstate sigma and now
we know that z here is twenty
one we know this from here so
this expression ie this thing here
yeah i can be other tool
like this this thing here evaluates to
forty two
and then what we do is we
go here
and we update our state
such that we set this extra forty
two and what this does is we
take the state from here and then
we simply swap in this forty two
here so we end up with a
new state where x is forty two
why is minus one and z is
twenty one and then we take our
expression t which was this experts y
and we
evaluated on the state that we have
solve for x we use forty two
and four why we use minus one
and then we sort of obviously end
up with devalue forty wasn't on here
so this was the one direction now
let's see it in the other direction
namely we take this expression t and
then we replace the occurrences of x
with e so when i look at
the expression a t it has exactly
one occurrence of x made me this
one and so i go in and
replace this occurrence of
ex with this expression that i had
to time see so then the new
expression here becomes two times c plus
y
and then i evaluate this on the
original estate sigma and when i look
up in sigma then i see that
the value of z is twenty one
in my sigma and the value of
y is minus one in my sigma
and then i see that in this
case this also evaluates to forty one
this was just a small example to
convince you the general proof as i
said will be in the homework
then we have a further proposition and
let's maybe take a pod with this
proposition means so it says an interstate
sigma
that is updated by setting the value
of x to whatever the expression he
evaluates in this state and this new
resulting state satisfies this assertion here for
t one and t to some expression
if and only if the original state
satisfies this formula here
where i have an in t one
replaced all occurrences of x with you
and i have also done the same
in t two
so actually there's not much going on
here there's just a little bit of
formula you're shuffling but let's maybe do
this do this proof here and look
at the individual steps for this small
case so we have this here which
is our right side
and then we say well this obviously
only holds if what t one evaluates
to in this in this state is
less than what two two evaluates two
in the state so in some sense
i pull this evaluation of these expressions
i pull that in so i have
this
only if that or this would be
less than that
and then the next step this should
look awfully familiar to you because we
have basically proven something about stuff that
looks a bit like this
already before so if we go back
one slide we have just
we have just proven that those two
things are the same or we have
not not really proven but i have
said that always see an example and
you will prove it in the homework
so let's assume it for now
and then what we can do here
is the useless thing that we have
just not proven and plug it in
here
and then we can basically do this
thing that we did before in reverse
so if this expression that we have
here evaluated on sigma
and is less than this expression evaluated
on sigma here
then obviously the sigma satisfies the assertion
that this expression
here is less than the other one
so these are some preliminary propositions that
he wants to get out of the
way mark or other relevant questions up
to now
okay so everybody's happy that's always nice
so then let's maybe continue
ah okay so we have only seen
this for this less for now and
of course we need to proof this
for every formula so formulas too often
not just consist of an expression is
just another expression but usually there's more
things going on than just less there's
usually some conjunctions implications other things
so one actually needs to prove this
for every formula and we will here
just strictly sketch how one could do
this and the idea would be that
one doesn't induction of the structure of
the formula
so this is one further of these
necessary prerequisites out of the way and
we will heavily use this in the
rest of the proof
so now let's continue so we actually
maybe we can go i'll go back
again to see so that you see
what we are trying to do
and named so this
and we want to do this induction
on the length m and we have
already proven for the base case where
ms zero that it works so now
what do we want to do as
we want to look at the inductive
case
and so let's go here
and here we have the induction hypothesis
that the statements already holds for m
minus one so if i have a
path of length m then it already
holds for all the steps except the
last one
and then i called the assertion at
this last point
u m minus one way of proving
it i call that b prime
and then as a first case let
us deal with statements so we look
at what happens when the thing that
happens between step n minus one and
that m is a statement and the
first statement is a very nice statement
that so many of the empty statement
so nothing happens here
so we know that the weakest precondition
for some formula b and the empty
statement is simply be itself again
and then we also know that b
prime a implies b
and this we get from local consistency
because we had assumed that the annotations
are locally consistent so we know that
this thing he olds
and then it is sort of obvious
because the state does not change if
i do nothing it's the same i
saw both for sigma am minus one
and sigma m they will both satisfy
this for me to be here
since maybe continue with a more interesting
case namely the case where we do
a right
at first glance it might seem more
interesting actually there's not so much more
interesting things going on because once again
a right does not modify the local
state so we once again have that
the that the state before at step
i minus one the sigma and minus
one simply stays the same when we
go to sigma
so it's completely the same nothing interesting
happened the weakest precondition once again the
simply be and then we have the
same argument as before that be prime
implies beam and then we also have
this argument once again that sigma m
minus one is the same sigma m
and both of them satisfy b
so i promised something more interesting so
actually let us see something more interesting
namely we have an assignment where we
assign
maybe it can increase the font of
this thing yes we have an assignment
where we assign an expression ie to
this variable x so first of all
let us think about what the state
after this thing looks like to the
state sigma m
will be i take the state before
and then i evaluate this expression m
m
his expression he
on the state that i had before
and then i update x so this
is all that happens here so our
new state here will look like this
and then once again because of local
consistency we had that the
do the annotation that we have at
this program point before the sbi prime
it needs to imply the weakest precondition
of this assignment
so this thing here